Lets assume that I'm working on a project, started to write a new function and my colleague is telling me:
"You know, we have an urgent issue, its in the "master" branch, please, switch and help us to resolve it"
Well, this things can happen.
Typing "git checkout master" ...
An error. What've happened?
Previously we only switched branches while having a clean status, and now we have an uncommitted changes in the index.html.
The error occured because checkout is having our back covered.
Because if it changed index.html to the one we have in "master" our uncommitted changes will be erased.
I have no moral right to commit it as commit assumes,
that we were doing something and made, maybe, small, but meaningful and holistic change to the project.
And currently I've just started to write a function, but didnt finish it yet.
Under no circumstances one cant commit this kind of broken and unfinished code to the project.
So what should we do with these changes, if we urgently need to switch to the other branch right now?
This kind of situation is of an ordinary one, so we should know how to resolve it.
There are 2 main ways for that:
First one - make checkout switch the branch, by using the "--force" flag or, shortly "-f"
By that checkout will just rewrite the files with the ones from "master".
You see, the switch was successful: index.html was changed to the version from the "master".
But now if we go back to fix ... You see, our changes are gone.
The "-f" flag's peculiar feature is that its sometimes used with no arguements at all
Just to cancel all the uncommitted changes.
For example, I've made some changes, some experiments in the working directory, maybe even added to index
and then I'm looking at it and, no, that will not do. How do clean it all up?
Call "git checkout -f HEAD" ...
As "HEAD" is a reference to the current branch we are switching to exactly where we were
So we are not switching the branch.
But the "-f" flag is saying we have to checkout, so all the files should be rewritten with the versions of the same branch
to which we are switching to.
So to the versions that are in the "HEAD" of the repository. Thats exactly what we need.
To keep it short we can even remove the "HEAD" as if branch is not set "checkout" will use the "HEAD" as the default.
Done, files are restored.
Now we have a clean status, as index changes were reset by the "-f" as well.
We've just had a look how to remove the changes.
Lets have a look at the alternative approach.
If we want to keep the changes, we can get use of the "git stash" command.
This command grabs all the uncommitted changes,
and removes them from the files and archives them in a special way inside git.
You see, the file is back to its initial state.
We have a clean status, so we can siwtch: "git checkout master" ...
And back.
You see, it works
Then, when I want to get my changes back "git stash pop"...
See, the changes are back in the file.
Therefore "git stash" allows us to preserve unfinished changes and then get back to them easilly.
Its important to keep in mind that technically git does not connect these saved changes to any particular branch or particular commit.
So one can always save the changes,
by just calling the "git stash" on one branch and apply "git stash pop" on the other branch.
If the file in the other branch, to which changes have to be applied
"index.html" in our case
is different in the branch from which we stashed the changes
then git might be having problems with applying these changes, or so called "merge conflict" will occur.
We will have a closer look to what that is and how to deal with this in our next videos.
Мы подробно рассмотрим, что это такое и как с этим быть в будущих выпусках.
Most of the time this "stash" problem happens due to an error.
While we were making stash on one branch and applied it to the other, albeit we wanted to apply to the one where we made changes initially.
Therefore we have to be carefull to where stash was made and where its going to be applied, so that dont shoot ourselfs in the foot.
"git stash" has some more features.
But to keep it straight we'll have a look at it in the other issue of our screencast,
that is dedicated to namely "git stash", so we could see how this command works in greater details.
For now lets get back to branching.
А сейчас давайте вернёмся к веткам.
Probably, after the last one you have an impression
that any uncommitted changes are blocking us from switching a branch.
Thats not true at all.
checkout only complains when the change is in the file that is different between the branches.
So the one he has to change.
In our case "index.html" is one in "fix" and different in "master".
what if file is same in both branches?
А что если файл в обоих ветках одинаковый?
That is quite typical. Most likely most files between the branches remain the same.
for instance, in our case "script.js" file in the "fix" branch wasnt changed. Its same as in "master".
All the changes that we've done in the fix were related to index.html and we didnt touch the "script.js".
Therefore if I delete the uncommitted changes and make some but in the script.js instead
(and here's our new status)
now call "git checkout master"...
You see, we switched.
No error this time, because when switching checkout is checking the repository
Aha, so the "script.js" file is same in both branches, therefore I dont need to change it.
And keeps the file as it is, without touching "script.js" at all.
Therefore the uncommitted changes remain there as they are.
Checkout makes a mark, you see "M" from modified, that means that the file was modified.
Thats for your information, so you know that the switch was successfull, but the uncommitted changes remain in a file.
We have a closer look at "index.html" to make sure that the switch was successfull.
Now its like that, so its aligned with the "master" branch.
Lets switch back ...
Switch successful. "index.html" was changed to the one we had in the "fix" branch.
"script.js" has uncommitted changes as it had before.
So the logic is the following: if file is different between the branches
or is present in one branch and removed from the other - we have an error.
If file is the same, changes are preserved.
I give it so much attention as this checkout behavior may lead
to the situation when the work done for one branch will get into another branch.
For example, in our case changes in the "script.js" file we've made on a "fix" branch
Maybe we even added them to index.
But if we switch to the master and call "git commit",
new commit will write all these changes to the "master" branch.
If thats not what we want, then as soon as we see this message from "checkout" we can switch to the previous branch,
finish something or archive our changes, using "git stash", depends on what are we trying to achieve.
Just pay attention while checking out to make sure you avoid this accident transfer of your changes between the branches.
At the same time there are cases in which this checkout behavior is on the contrary, very useful.
For example, lets get back at 2 commits ago, the moment when we didnt create a "fix" branch yet.
Its not always obvious when you need a new branch.
You might start working on master, thinking that the change is trivial, change this, commit
But then you realize you also have to change this and this. All of a sudden it a brand new feature, way bigger than you thought of it
You cant finish it right now and you have to put it into its own branch.
Good news everyone! Git makes it trivial.
If I create a new branch right now and switch to it all the uncommitted changes are going to be inside it.
In other words, running...
As you can see on the image here, "fix" branch was created that is pointing to the current commit
and "checkout" switched HEAD right to it.
As both master and fix are now pointing at the same commit there are no changes between them.
So all the uncommitted changes were saved while we switched.
Of course I can get back to "master" and switch to "fix" again.
As you see, the uncommitted changes remain.
They do not stop us from switching between 2 identical branches.
But now if I commit all as I did while being at "master"
its saved in "fix" as intended.
I also note that its easy to move the changes to the new branch as they were not committed.
What if we accidentally made some commits in the wrong branch?
Well, it can happen.
More good news, its something we can fix easilly as we'll see in the next issue.